<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The bruising of the serpents head A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse September 9. 1621. By Roger Ley Maister of Arts, and minister of Gods word in Shoreditch.</title>
            <author>Ley, Roger, b. 1593 or 4.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05416</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103082</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838840</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838840</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3229</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05416)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3229)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 843:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The bruising of the serpents head A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse September 9. 1621. By Roger Ley Maister of Arts, and minister of Gods word in Shoreditch.</title>
                  <author>Ley, Roger, b. 1593 or 4.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 49, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Dawson for Nicholas Bourne, and are to be sold at his shop at the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3229:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3229:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BRVISING OF THE SERPENTS Head.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at Pauls Croſſe <hi>September</hi> 9. 1621.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> ROGER LEY Maiſter of Arts, and Miniſter of Gods Word in <hi>Shoreditch.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GEN. 3.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I will put enmity betweene thee and the Woman, and betweene thy ſeede and her ſeede: it ſhall bruiſe thy Head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his Heele.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Dawſon</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3229:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3229:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. ROBERT DVCIE Alderman of <hi>London peace and ſaluation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our eare hath beene partaker of that I nowe preſent to your eye. In all things vſually one ſenſe maketh way for the other, and the ſecond perfecteth the firſt: for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring doth render that but farre off, which ſeeing giueth neerer hand. A ſpeaker is then happieſt in his labour, when words are permanent and fixed. And that, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:3229:3"/>in the heart and meditation of the hearer, when the Spirit and finger of God, by zeale and induſtrious labour printeth them there, as ſo many engrauen letters: or when to helpe memory, they are expoſed to publique view; for ſounds doe paſſe in the aire, this hath the priuiledge of a conſtant continuance. Sermons deliuered in that audience, are principally for the gouernours of this Honourable Cittie. Therefore I offer it to you by dedication, as I did before in ſpeaking vnto many. Many were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, you a preſent hearer in the time of vacation, when your place being Sheriffe required reſidence. Moreouer, being for a time a labourer in your Pariſh, as ſmaller riuers vſe not to breake out into ſeuerall Chanels if one be preſerued full: I let this come to you among the reſt, as with a greater confluence. Small I terme this gift in reſpect of the Authour, and his ſufficience. The words eminence which may be ſeene in planneſſe, and natiue ſimplicity; is onely worth the reckoning. God the great guide of this
<pb facs="tcp:3229:3"/>world hath giuen the ſmalleſt ſtarres their influence. And the milky circle in Heauen (ſo it is called) conſiſteth of thoſe ſtarres that are ſcarce diſcernable, they are not for that excluded from the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament. For although the great Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher ſuppoſed that circle to be lower, and out of the Heauens: yet the fictions of vnskilfull antiquity made it the way to Paradiſe, and the caeleſtiall Court. My deſire is, that the word being forcible in the meaneſt inſtrument, may moue in the Orbe by this publique paſſage, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect on earth, and yeeld the way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: For this end, I hold it better to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the proſperous ſucceſſe of it to him aboue, that committed the deliuerance to me: then to feare the vncertaine cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of a Criticke. This being the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Writer, I deſire the Readers true practiſe, and entertainment may make it good.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your vnfained well-willer, in all obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance and due reſpect.
ROGER LEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3229:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3229:4"/>
            <head>THE BRVISING OF THE Serpents Head. At Pauls Croſſe. <hi>September.</hi> 1621.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LVKE, 11.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>When a ſtrong man armed keepeth his palace, his goods are in peace.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. <hi>But when a ſtronger then he ſhall come vpon him and ouercome him, he taketh from him all his Armour wherin he truſted and diuideth his ſpoiles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="23">23. <hi>He that is not with me, is againſt me, and he that gathereth not with me, ſcattereth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a fault grieuous and yet too common, that good things are leaſt eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: but of all errours the baſeſt is to miſconſter good actions and to depraue the ſhining worth of excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. This as it is the baſeſt, ſo the laſt ſhift of men har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened againſt goodneſſe, for when the deſart of others ſeemeth to touch and wound their inſufficience: then they caſt blemiſhes
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3229:5"/>vpon that which was feared to lay ſome blots vpon their vnworthineſſe. The ſtory of our Sauiour affords vs an incomparable example. He came to his owne, and his owne receiued him not. He came not among them empty handed without fauours, nor led an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable life: but all his workes were witneſſes of his loue, and all their wants and miſeries euident declarers of an incomparable working, Hauing now caſt out a Deuill which made the people wonder, the Phariſees ſwelling with enuie ſaid he did it by the power of the chiefe Deuill, ſo to diſgrace the worke they could not hinder. Againſt theſe men he directs his ſpeech, and ſheweth in them their intollerable blaſphemie, a ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, neuer to haue pardon. Our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Hiſtory then ſetteth out a double conflict of Chriſt the King and Sauiour of the world againſt Satan the enemie of mankind, the Deuill in the body and in the tongue: in the body of a poore man poſſeſt, in the tongue of the proud and rebellious Phariſees. The one was a Deuill blind and dumbe, the other a ſeeing and a ſlandering aduerſary. Becauſe violence doth not make an enemie ſo dangerous as when craft conueyeth his enterpriſe by ſome ſecret vndermining; the blind and dumbe man ſoone cured where the enemie ſhewed himſelfe by force, but theſe cauillers vnder whoſe lips lay hid the poyſon of Aſps, were not ſo ſoone put to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. Theſe Phariſees ſeemed holy men, they called the chiefe Deuill <hi>Belzebub</hi> out of zeale and a deuout pretence in deteſtation of their anceſtours idolatry, who worſhipped <hi>Baal,</hi> and among ſeuerall kinds of that heatheniſh idoll (which had many names accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the places of worſhip) <hi>Baalzebub;</hi> whoſe name they now abhord. And becauſe all things require go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, they ſuppoſed <hi>Belzebub</hi> the chiefe in hel, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing withall ſo many miracles performed by Chriſt they ſaid he did combine with the chiefe Deuill and by that power caſt them out. This calumnie is confuted
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3229:5"/>by ſundry arguments. Firſt, out of the ſeuenteenth verſe. Euery Kingdome deuided againſt it ſelfe is brought to deſolation, and a houſe deuided againſt it ſelfe cannot ſtand. If Satan alſo be deuided againſt himſelfe, and <hi>Belzebub</hi> the chiefe ioyne with Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the leſſe; how could that gouernment in dure?</p>
            <p>The ſecond argument we haue verſe, 19. Their iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was partiall and with reſpect of perſons, for their children caſt out Deuills and had no blame. He mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Iewiſh exorciſts, who had a power giuen them from aboue by calling vpon Gods name to caſt out theſe vncleane ſpirits. It is more then probable theſe Iewes did caſt them out by vſing the name of Chriſt which then was become famous. <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaith to our Sauiour, <hi>Marke</hi> 9.38. Maiſter we ſaw one caſting out Deuills in thy name and he followeth not vs. Theſe then eſcaped the Iewiſh hatred, but Chriſt did not: therefore hee inferreth againſt them, they ſhall be your iudges to condemne you, that <hi>malice</hi> the cauſe of <hi>ſlander,</hi> &amp; that the mother of falſehood haue caſt vpon me this iniuſtimputation. A thir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> argument is in theſe words. A ſtrong man keepeth his houſe and goods vntill a ſtronger force him out and take poſſeſſion in his place. I doe this expelling him with my word: therefore his power is ſubiect vnto mine, and my miracle is true; yee ought then to embrace my ſaying, and to ſtand to my cauſe confirmed with ſuch cleere teſtimony: or to be ſcattered in your fond deuiſes, ſo to reape the fruite of your owne folly.</p>
            <p>In the handling of theſe words I meane not to ſtand ſo much vpon poſſeſſion of the body, and of Chriſt the deliuerer: but that the ſubiect may ſomething ſute with the eminence of this place, and the full ſcope and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the words: rather ſhew a recouering of the ſoule, a renewing of the world, and a ſubduing of ſinne by the Goſpell. For the conſent of interpreters extend this ſaying to this as the full and perfect meaning, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3229:6"/>pounding it not merely of a bodily diſpoſſeſſion, but of the whole proceeding of Chriſt in the ſtrength of his Kingdome. The words yeeld the ſame of neceſſity, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> all his armour, the entering his palace, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding his ſpoiles, cannot limit this victory to a bodily deliuerance alone. <hi>Nos quondam arma eius regnique mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiam in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s ſuum redegit</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Hilarie.</hi> Chriſt hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vs who were once the Deuills armour and force of his Kingdome, and brought vs vnder his owne power. The whole world is the houſe of <hi>Belzebub,</hi> ſo <hi>Eraſmus.</hi> And <hi>Caluin, quicquid corporibus praeſtitit Chriſtus ad ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas referri voluit,</hi> whatſoeuer Chriſt performed to the body, he would haue the ſame referd vnto the ſoule. It is plainly ſhowne from the 24. Verſe. of this Chapter following the Text immediately. He compareth the nation of the Iewes to a man poſſeſt as the Deuills houſe. (S. <hi>Mathew</hi> maketh it more plaine) Chriſt did driue him out and clenſed the houſe by his Goſpell, but becauſe they entertained his words with ſcorne and neglected him; the houſe was empty: then commeth the vncleane ſpirit with ſeauen worſe then himſelfe, who finding the houſe emptie ſwept and garniſhed, he maketh it his habitation, and the end thereof is worſe then the beginning. So dangerous a ſinne is Apoſtacy, and ſo truly did hee threaten that wicked generation being rebels againſt the truth: for what decayed houſe, or miſerable ruine of any building can compare with thoſe emptie Iewes, that would not acknowledge their Lord?</p>
            <p>And that which <hi>Eſay</hi> the Prophet ſpake of the ſoule Cap. 53. verſe 4. He tooke our infirmities and bare our ſickneſſes, meaning ſinne and the maladies of the mind: S. <hi>Mathew</hi> chap. 8. verſe 17. applieth to caſting out of Deuills and curing of diſeaſes. For both are the worke of one Lord, for one and the ſame end to make vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him the onely redeemer. As the battering of the walls of a Citty, is but a preparatiue to handy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3229:6"/>ſtrokes and the ouerthrow of the dwellers: ſo the caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of Satan from the body the caſe and outſide of the ſoule, is a ſigne of ſauing power that cureth both ſoule and body, and will expell the enemie from all his vſurped places. <hi>Dauid</hi> reaſoned from one good turne to another, 1. <hi>Samuel</hi> 17.36. Thy ſeruant ſlue both the Lyon and the Beare, and this vncircumciſed Philiſtim ſhall be as one of them ſeeing he hath defied the armies of the liuing God. Moreouer the Lord that deliuered me from the paw of the Lyon and the beare, he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me out of the hand of this Philiſtim, in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner theſe words of Chriſt take occaſion from the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, to expreſſe his Soueraigne might in redeeming from the paw of hell and deſtruction. Let vs therefore take the whole world for a haunted houſe. We find it ſo <hi>Iob</hi> 1.7. I come (ſaith he) from going to and fro in the earth, and from walking vp and downe in it. The greateſt ſtrength of it his weapons and munition, the greateſt wit and policy of it, if it be fooliſhneſſe with God as the Apoſtle calls it, it cannot but ſauour of the wiſdome of this Serpent.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> If theſe places be the prime of our microcoſme, the head and glory of all our Iland they cannot but be aſſaulted. And if the cry of vices be not vntrue, the walking of ſome dangerous ſpirit may raiſe vp our ſuſpition and complaint. Whoſe puiſance to ſhew, whoſe dealing to diſcouer, and to vncaſe his villanie that lurketh in our preſence; as in it ſelfe is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable: ſo more auailable when the power of heauen is ſhowne that ouerthrowes it. In the ſeeing of both we may doe as the world vſually doth, take part with the ſtronger ſide. To one we muſtioyne, no ſtaying in the middeſt. Chriſt ſaith ſo in the laſt of theſe verſes. He that is not with me is againſt me. That God is ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: and his quarrell ſafer, the beginning ſpeaketh eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently. Chriſt entreth into the ſtrong mans Palace, Ouercommeth him, taketh from him all his armour wherein he truſted, and deuideth his ſpoiles. I find then
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3229:7"/>in this Text that which either is expreſt or implyed in euery Sermon, a Doctrine and a Vſe: the ſtrength of our Sauiour affirmed, and our obedient ſeruice enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. In the firſt of theſe a power of vſurpation and a power of iuriſdiction. In the vſurped power we find two parts: the ſtrong mans induſtry. He is armed and keepeth his Palace: and his ſecurity, his goods are in peace. The lawfull power hath two parts: Chriſts vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory: But when a ſtronger then he ſhall come vppon him and ouercome him: and his gaine: he taketh from him all his armour wherein he truſted and deuideth his ſpoiles. The next Verſe is a reproofe of vnprofitable ſeruants which make no vſe of this benefit. Hee ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in them two things, a baſe negligence, and a vaine confidence. Firſt, the negligent ſtander by that is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hot nor cold, is caſt out as diſtaſted by his palate, he that is not with me is againſt me. Secondly, his vaine hope. Let him heape, and build, and frame his workes together: all is to be blowne away with the breath of Gods diſpleaſure, hee that gathereth not with me ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth. Of theſe parts in order.</p>
            <p>
               <label>His induſtry, when a ſtrong man armed keepeth his Palace.</label>
            </p>
            <p>The beginning hauing dwelt longer vpon the ſence of the words to free them from obſcurity, each part may be paſt ouer with better expedition. Theſe firſt words note vnto vs the power of our enemie called the ſtrong Man, and his diligence, he is armed and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his Palace. Hard it is to match with one ſo well prouided. Our Sauiour ſpeaketh of him thus, Now is the Prince of this world caſt out, <hi>Iohn</hi> 21.31. And to ſhew, we might imagine ſomething aboue the world, and the reach of mortall powers (becauſe the greateſt Potentate is but an arme of fleſh) he is called the God of the world, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. In whom the God of this world
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3229:7"/>hath blinded the eies of them that beleeue not. Hee is called the Prince of the power of the aire. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Sunt magnapars corum quae in imperijs geruntur &amp; fiunt</hi> ſaith <hi>Peucer.</hi> In the buſines of Kingdomes they haue a hand and a great ſtroke. <hi>Inſidiantur atrocius ijs qui ad gubernaculaſedent</hi> ſaith the ſame Authour: They aſſault them moſt dangerouſly, who ſit at the helme of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and he addeth the reaſon that the diſeaſe hauing gotten and poſſeſt the head, the infection might ſpread abroad vpon the body, and deſtroy all like a common peſtilence. It was for ſome thing he fell to this temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in aſſaulting Chriſt whom he felt ſo impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. All theſe things will I giue thee, ſhe wing him the world and glory of it. He had ſome ſhow for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, although his reaſon was vnſound: ſaying, it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto mee, and to whomſoeuer I will I giue it. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.6. This authoritie is firſt and principall in the Infidels, who wanting the true guide by an ineuitable fall doe light vpon the falſe. In them he ruleth and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them on to his owne ends, and theſe are of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt power, and poſſeſſe the chiefe roomes in his houſe by domineering in the world. That we may not faile of the truth, haue recourſe vnto the fountaine and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning which vſually giues the cleereſt euidence, wee ſhall find greatneſſe and vngodlineſſe grow together. The firſt Citty that was built had <hi>Cain</hi> to be the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, called <hi>Enoch</hi> after his ſonnes name. From him came <hi>Lamech,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> and from that wicked race deſcended the great men of the earth. <hi>Iabal</hi> the father of ſuch as dwell in tents, <hi>Iubal</hi> of skilfull muſicians, and <hi>Tubal Cain</hi> of artificers in braſſe and yron. No words of <hi>Abel</hi> but religion and ſlaughter together. Of <hi>Seth</hi> and <hi>Enos</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming at laſt in <hi>Abels</hi> roome, it is reported, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.26. Then (as if it had beene long looked for before) then beganne men to call vpon the name of the Lord. But time the great friend and enemie to the earth, as it brought about this good turne, did weare out that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3229:8"/>ſeaſon.
<note place="margin">Gen. 6.1.</note> For when they beganne to multiply, the ſonnes of God, tooke vnto them the daughters of men, and from ſo bad a copulation, we could not expect but a like progenie: the flood ſwept away the generation at laſt, only eight were found fit to be ſaued in the Arke, and one <hi>Cham</hi> in the company. After this beginning to relate what followed, though briefely were too tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Let vs looke at our owne times, find we not the ſtrong man armed in his Palace? How are the ſpacious places and gardens of the world inhabited by them that know not the worſhip of God? And in Chriſtian Kingdomes how hath idolatry preuailed, and prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the higheſt? a ſinne to ſtates both dangerous and fatall: it often ouerthrew the Iewes, and now hath ſo exaſperated the Iudge of the earth, that Turkiſh cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath cut of the goodlieſt branches of this Vine, and that Citty which the Tartarian conquerour iudged fit to command the world, is become the chiefe ſeate of this Mahometant tyrant. Roome the other eye of Europe helpes him forward by hindring a reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to this effect the Dragon and the Beaſt ioyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their forces. Let none thinke this imputation is iniuſt, time and euill cuſtome make way to a deſtroyer by ſoiling religion with ſuperſtition and idolatry. The ſpirit of God ſpeaketh ſo much almoſt in plaine termes, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 9.20. When the Angels were looſed from the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Euphrates, to bring ſo many millions to kill the third part of men; yet the reſt of men repented not of the workes of their hands, that they ſhould not worſhip Deuils, and idols of gold, and ſiluer, and braſſe, and ſtone, and wood, which neither can ſee, nor heare, nor walke. Who hath come from the riuer Euphrates, and ſlaine ſo many but the Turke? bringing ſo many mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions to deſtroy. Of whom hath he ſlaine them but of Chriſtians? and who worſhip Images but the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? the followers of <hi>Mahomet</hi> hate idoles, and the profeſſors of Chriſt are in loue with them. By the way
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3229:8"/>then, ſee how little good Chriſtendome can expect while Antichriſt and his Kingdome ſtand. In the meane time ſee the ſtrong man armed keeping his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, the two imperiall Citties, one rent from the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, the other renting in pieces the truth of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <hi>Romulus</hi> built it at firſt in blood, and that in the blood of a brother, ſince hauing got an Empire by the euerie and oppreſſion, now ſupports it ſelfe the ſame way, as if it would ratifie that maxime in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy: We are nouriſhed by thoſe meanes from whence we ariſe and ſpring vp. For now a Monarchie ouer the conſcience, a new priuiledge is that they chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, cruelty to vphold it, and commodity gleaned in deuotion to vphold themſelues: theſe are the chiefe Pillars to maintaine their ſtate. When Chriſt came in perſon to bind this ſtrong man, the Romans had <hi>Iury</hi> vnder their dominion, <hi>Herode</hi> an <hi>Idumean</hi> was their King, religion was corrupted with traditions, the ſects of Saducees and Phariſees made a diuiſion within: and therefore their outward miſerie was the greater. And at our Sauiours ſecond comming, this is his owne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, The Sonne of man ſhall not find faith vpon the earth, ſo mightily doth this ſtrong man enlarge his territories. Come vnto Gods owne houſe his Church, where religion is truly profeſt, where God hath his Church, he will haue his Chappell, hauing moſt cauſe to be ſtirre himſelfe leaſt he be a looſer, thether hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerts his greateſt forces to worke in all ſorts and by all deuiſes. And that two waies, either to quench the leaſt ſparkes that are to aduance the truth, or to depraue and corrupt it by turning matters the wrong way, and mixing euill with the good. Sometimes he is a ſolicitor to ſet forwards his owne buſines in conſultations. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times he helpes the Iudge in giuing ſentence. He can doe as with <hi>Achabs</hi> Prophets enter and ſeduce in the place of ſanctity. He aduanceth many men into offices, and ſpecially where money makes the way, for thoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3229:9"/>are his vſuall ſtaires. When hee hath ſet them vp they muſt honour their Patron and benefactor, and he a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle direct them in execution. And that no place may want him, in the good actions of many, hee foiſteth ſome lameneſſe, and cloggeth the endeauours of honeſt men.</p>
            <p>This ſtrong man is not armed alone, but skill can doe equall miſchiefe, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14. Satan is transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into an Angell of light. Not in ſhape, for the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels haue no countenance, or viſible forme; but as <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie</hi> ſaith, he counterfeiteth holineſſe, that his counſells may be heard. Like a corrupt Tradeſman, hee can ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſticate his vnprofitable commodity, and colour his harmes with guilded pretences. In the Church he can ſow faction vnder pretence of zeale, and cheriſh curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity vnder tendernes of conſcience. In the common affaires of this life, he can make bribery walke vnder the name of thankfulnes, and gratuitie: oppreſſion vnder thrift, pride vnder commendable faſhion and ciuility. Theſe trickes make him dance in a net, gulling the world as it were in laughter, and by his policies he will preuaile. The reaſon is if vice were ſeene in his owne apparell, it would ſcare the beholder with a fearefull and vgly viſage, therfore he doth furniſh it vp with the choiſeſt ornaments, and paints ouer the deformities with better ſhowes, to make it paſſe for commendable. What thing is ſo bad or baſe, but one caſſiering modeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and an honeſt minde, will by wit and worldly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons iuſtifie and make good. So when the heart is ſet vpon pleaſure, and the deſire beginnes to burne after ſome particular gaine: politicke reſolution perſwades either it may be iuſt, or not ſo bad as ſome thinke, either a tollerable or a neceſſary euill. Heereupon it followeth that among Chriſtians, ſome for their profit and content will defend thoſe faults, which the wiſer Heathen haue deteſted in their writings. As he could not haue dealt with <hi>Saul</hi> that came to him in his troubles, but in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3229:9"/>ſhape of <hi>Samuel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam 28.13.</note> the witch ſaid gods are come out of the earth: ſo could he not haue the applauſe of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple world, but by an earthly diuinity, when new found reaſons, and crafty proiects turne matters into another mould, and rob the great theefe, euen ſinne of his owne appearance. Neither could we haue among vs ſo much profeſſing, and little good dealing, except there were this myſterie of hypocriſie. Heere then wefeele him, heere we haue iuſt cauſe to feare him; <hi>daemon meridianus</hi> this Deuill at noone day is moſt dangerous: As at firſt in Paradiſe and vnder the Serpent hee got the day, ſo doth he in the Church of God, and by his ſubtilty. S.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern. ſuper cantica. Ser.</hi> 33</note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> complaind in his times that the Church of God had three aduerſaries, then did the night of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry draw on farre, brought in by the laſt of the three. The firſt was the feare of the night, when tyrants did perſecute the Martyrs in the primitiue Church. The ſecond was the arrow that flyeth by day, the fond opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of hereſie, flying by the inuention of the ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vpon the feathers of vaine glory. But (ſaith he) the patience of the Saints ouercame the firſt, and the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the learned deſtroyed the ſecond. The third was the peſtilence in the darkeneſſe the ſinne of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and falſe appearance that nothing could with ſtand: they name Chriſt and ſerue Antichriſt, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe God and deny him alſo. Therefore he taketh vp the complaint of <hi>Hezekia,</hi> Behold in peace bitternes bitternes: the Church was then worſt of all. <hi>Amara prius in caede martyrum, amarior poſt in conflictu haeretieo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, amariffima nunc in moribus domeſticorum.</hi> Bitternes at firſt in the death of Martyrs, bitternes in corrupted manners. May not reformation renew a complaint, and ſay the world is alwaies like it ſelfe. As the hotteſt weather doth ſooneſt putrifie: ſo abundance of peace and many bleſſings; haue not theſe made the rottenes come neerer to the heart? Let a generall diſcourſe which cannot tarrie, point at the tops of a few ill fruits
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3229:10"/>and eaſieſt diſcerned. Our women turnd into the ſhapes of men, our men and eſpecially they of the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants ranke growne effeminate. Drunkeneſſe ſo great that to caſt out this Deuill were a miracle indeede, to bring in requeſt againe the moderate and temperate li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of ancient times. And that euery age may bring vp ſome new monſter, <hi>fumum vendunt &amp; fumo pereunt,</hi> the ſelling of fume, immoderate ſmooking waſteth both the body and the purſe; a miſchiefe vnheard of in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages befitting no ſeaſon but this of the doting and declining world. Garments the memorials of ſinne ſhould teach vs our loſſes and our ſorrow, when <hi>Adam</hi> had forſaken God and his innocence forſaken him, ſhame and neceſſity procured a couering for his naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But now they are not ſo much remembrancers of the old;
<note place="margin">Cyp. de diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na &amp; habitu. Varg.</note> as actors of new ſinnes; and plaine repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of each idle fancie: S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> complained in his time, that when God had ſaid thou canſt not make one haire white or blacke, the women did confute the Scripture, and turnd their haire to yellow; the colour he did miſlike as too ominous of hell fire; <hi>malo praeſagio futurorumcapillos iam tibi flammeos auſpicaris,</hi> with an ill preſage of what was to follow they flamed already. Now this colour is fallen about the necke and other places, that poore whitenes the token of innocence and ſincerity weareth out of requeſt. But theſe follies may plead cuſtome, and it ſeeme a vaine thing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict them. This ſuperficiall badnes being ſo confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and like to hold his owne, cannot but ſuppoſe a worſe whereon it builds. Where the face of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on appeareth outwardly any way; it ſheweth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts to be worſe deformed: Yet thus muſt it be where truth doth ſhine ſo cleere, and men loue darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe more then light: if the Church yeeld not good fruit, it muſt needs ouerflow with weeds, knowledge doth make it ranke and proud. And when the beames of ſupernaturall direction fall downe in ſo powerfull a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3229:10"/>manner, yet obſtinacie beateth backe theſe gracious of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, refuſing the influence, ſtrange and vnnaturall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects muſt needs follow. For as the carcaſſe of a man is more noiſome then the putrefaction of fruits and plants, becauſe the temper exceld them in the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: ſo where much good is, and bleſſedneſſe it ſelfe turned into ſurfeit, thoſe declinations are moſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</p>
            <p>We haue now ſeene the ſtrong man armed keeping his Palace, within and without the Church, his ſtrength and policy ioyned together: but hitherto we haue one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly traced him as Prince of the Aire. Now let our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe be <hi>ſub tecto,</hi> as well as <hi>ſub dio,</hi> ſee his manſion and enter his roofe a while: that as his intents are to bring confuſion and publique miſerie, we may now ſee the place of reſidence whence theſe plots and ſtratagems haue their hatching. Euery man by nature is the child of wrath, conceiued in ſinne and being readieſt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the worſt, way eaſily liſteneth to this euill maſter. He inſinuateth himſelfe by ſweete and pleaſant begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, then cuſtome giueth him poſſeſſion, at laſt the ſoule and body become the houſe, and fall ſubiect to his gouernment. Witchcraft doth ſometimes mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt his hatred to the body, when God giueth him leaue to torment the outward part of the creature, in heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mercy giuing warning to euery ſpectator, what it is to be vnder this helliſh tyranny. Such accidens come among vs for this end to draw vp the mindes loaded with earthly cares to theſe conſiderations. Theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances as ſtrange things haue beene plaid, and made matters of paſtime, but may ſerue for edification. For thereby we learne the truth of eternall life. If a bad ſpirit come and offer his ſeruice to torment, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude there is a good ſpirit to ſaue, that ſpirituall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers doe gouerne theſe earthly affaires, and a Diuine power commandeth all. We learne the loue of God that fuffereth him not to hurt all as well as ſome few:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3229:11"/>the truth of religion which his ſlaues doe firſt renounce, and then he markes them for his owne; firſt they denie Baptiſme, then his owne Sacraments ſucceede to make them faſt. And why doth hee not ſeaſe vpon euery adulterous body? the reaſon is God holds him in. Or that hee ſnatcheth not away the ſoules of ſuch as ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine miſchiefe, the cauſe is Gods mercy who ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth execution, not ſuffering to proceede according to deſert,
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.9.</note> as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſheweth, the Lord is not ſlack concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his promiſe as ſome thinke, <hi>But is long ſuffering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs not willing any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance.</hi> Theſe trialls may come vpon the good becauſe in them ſome parcell of ſinne remaineth, <hi>Iobs</hi> body was not exempted from this tormentor, but let wicked men be perſwaded, he ruleth them and their affaires; perhaps they proſper and therefore beleeue it not: it is a cold comfort when he vſeth them for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and delighteth in their proſperity. In the minde he can darken the motions of vnderſtanding, dazle and poſſeſſe the fancie, hinder the outward ſences and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude them, he can ſtirre vp the appetite, and inflame the deſires of them he tempteth, and ſuppreſſe them againe as he thinketh good.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De operib. Dei part.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</note> Onely as <hi>Zanchy</hi> ſaith (who ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all theſe at large) hee cannot remoue or turne the will, God hath giuen a man his reſolution free, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the hinge that moueth all about, &amp; the wheele by which the actions are turned: he may tempt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade he cannot command; in the middeſt of violent aſſaults, God hath left a man ſo much liberty.</p>
            <p>I will end this point with a reaſon why the Lord doth grant him this ſtrength. The wofull cauſe is the ſinne of man. He tempted <hi>Eue</hi> in the ſhape of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent by outward inuaſion, and vttered his meaning to Chriſt in that temptation by outward dealing. For they were innocent and free from ſinne, he could take no footing in the inward affections: but now an euill heart giues him an eaſie paſſage to enter and come in,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3229:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>thereupon he is more powerfull and vnreſiſtable. As originall ſinne doth giue him entrance, euill practiſe doth further his dominion. The breaking of Gods commandement is the cauſe, that the reiecting of one ruler leading to peace and bleſſednes; cauſeth ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the ſlauiſh labour of ſo vile a commander. For this is Gods order, firſt to giue a Law, and afterwards to turne ouer him that ſtubburnly offendeth to this his executioner. S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth this was the reaſon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels did fall ſo fearefully,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe when they knew God they glorified him not as God, neither were thankefull, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came vaine in their imaginations, their fooliſh heart was dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened.</hi> Therefore God gaue them ouer to a reprobate minde, and to do things not conuenient as the Apoſtle rehearſeth. The light of nature taught them better things then their liues did expreſſe. Which knowledge is ſo great, that by it way may be made for Diuine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. <hi>Lactantius</hi> is bold to affirme ſo much of the knowledge of Infidels.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L. diu. inſt. cap.</hi> 5</note> 
               <hi>Quod ſi vel Orpheus vel hi noſtri quae natura ducente ſenſerunt in perpetuum defendiſſent, ean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem quam nos ſequimur doctrinam comprehenſa veritate te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuiſſent.</hi> If Orpheus and ſuch like had conſtantly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taind thoſe things which nature taught them, they would at laſt haue come to the Doctrine which we doe follow. This is the reaſon, why the power of ſpirituall tyrannie is ſo great among the Heathen, becauſe they tranſgreſſe the rules of nature and their conſcience. Now wherefore hee ſhould ſcourge the Church, and preuaile ſo much, there cannot but be greater reaſon. For where a full hand powreth out benefits in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and groſſe vnthankfulnes returneth backe to heauen from whence they flow: God may then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine as he did with <hi>Eſay,
<note place="margin">Eſay 1.2.</note> I haue nouriſhed and brought vp children, and they haue rebelled againſt me.</hi> And except it were for the choſens ſake, for Gods glory, and his ſeruice which muſt haue an abiding place, how could a Church polluted with impiety expect any mercy or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3229:12"/>continuance? Beſides, the deuils rage doth glorifie God the more by exerciſing the faithfull, who againſt the ſtreame of ſinne, keepe an euen courſe, and a ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt profeſſion.</p>
            <p>This for the reaſon of his progreſſe and ſtrength. In this Doctrine obſerue yet a limitation: Theſe ſpirituall powers are not ſuch abſolute Lords to doe what they liſt among any, no not among Infidels, though they be powers of darkneſſe: but onely ſo farre as God ſeeth fit in iuſt iudgement to execute his iuſt wrath. God tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the hearts of the Aegyptians to his people, to haſten them out of the land, and furniſhed them with iewels for their iourney. Chriſt was at that Counſell which gaue ſentence for his owne death, or elſe it could not haue gone forwards. Well may <hi>Hoſius</hi> alledge euen that for the defence of Counſels, that the iudgement of the Church is not deſtitute of the holy Spirit. For <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas</hi> the high Prieſt (or Pope of the Iewes if we may ſo call him,
<note place="margin">Iohn 11.50.</note> ſpake by inſpiration. <hi>It is neceſſary that one die for the people, and that the whole Nationperiſh not.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs conceiue his dominion very large and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as the Text names it, a Hall or a Palace, as if a Cottage or meane dwellings did not containe him: his working is by permiſſion, hee is ſet on as a maſtife, and pulled off againe by Gods appointment and pleaſure. Otherwiſe his owne habitation is the the deepe, as appeareth, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.31. When the Legion was caſt out of the man, they made ſupplication to Chriſt not to ſend them into the deepe, but giue them more imployment by allowing their entrance into the the heard of ſwine. It is then euident hell is his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, except God imploy and ſuffer him. So in the middeſt of his working a hand aboue reſtraineth him from proſecuting his malice with extreamities, this is the worlds comfort, his intents are limited. And ſo much of the ſtrong mans induſtry, <hi>He is armed and keapeth his Palace,</hi> the next part followeth, <hi>His goods are in Peace,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:3229:12"/>which is his ſecuritie.</p>
            <p>I gather two obſeruations from theſe words. Firſt, none can deliuer himſelfe from ſpirituall bondage, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> his goods are in peace. When wickednes hath got the vpper hand, and temptation borne the ſway: vice groweth into a habite, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome is a ſecond nature. Hardly can one maſter it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euen ground, but when theſe bonds doe fetter a wicked perſon, and diſarme him of his owne right: he doth liue at anothers becke, and how can he then make head againe to purpoſe, or recouer himſelfe by ſtrong reſiſtance? The goods cannot ſhake of the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, nor the houſe expell the maſter, ſuch are offendors in continuing euill: led as ſlaues, and dragd along as ſheepe vnto the ſlaughter, fallen into a pit whence they cannot come out, or quit themſelues againe. Which ſhould teach euery one not to yeeld at firſt, leaſt giuing the raines to his managing, their falls grow fearefull, and their dangers almoſt deſperate: yet for them thus hardened in vice, becauſe Diuinity giueth a ſalue for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſore they muſt endeauour and diſtruſt their owne power. Now wreſtling is able to ſhake off his yoake, but in vſing the meanes which God hath appointed, whereby they denie themſelues: and adding to their labour conſtant prayer and inuocation: they take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them an eaſie yoake and a light burden of their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour the ſtronger man. Repentance vndoeth the knot which tied the ſoule in this captiuity: prayer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth all power in him that prayeth, euen as among men he that asketh helpe of another, and maketh daily ſupplication, doth ſhew how little his owne ability can performe, and how ill the matter goeth with him. Thus ſorrow for ſinne, repentance, prayer, and ſtedfaſt endeauour ioyned: may worke a cure vnder God, and that be done vnder the ſaſegard of the Almighty, that none of himſelfe can compaſſe Prayer and faſting was able to expell the deuill which the Diſciples could not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3229:13"/>caſt out. Let this conſideration correct their miſtaking, who hope to conquer and ſhake of their ſinnes, not v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing religious meanes and exerciſes. No hope to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in ſuch combates without a full repentance, with an abſolute reſignation of the ſoule into the Sauiours hand. See heere the power of a poore captiue in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, faſtened in the nets of his owne weauing, entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the labarinth of his folly, no way to ſaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>His goods are in Peace.</label>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the words yeeld vs this Doctrine. Satan fighteth not againſt himſelfe to diſaduantage or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace his gouernment, but keepeth cloſe together, and tieth his inſtruments in a ſtrong confederacy that their vniting may make him more inuincible. The words import ſo much. <hi>His goods are in Peace.</hi> Sometimes it muſt needs be otherwiſe with Chriſt and his Goſpell, for when vngodlines doth glue and cling together, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther among his owne or others; hee commeth often with ſtir and diuiſion, and renteth all in peeces for a time. Heere then we find the caſe variable, ſometimes wickednes findeth great diſagreement, as experience teacheth; ſometimes great league and fellowſhip, as both experience and this Text doe manifeſt; ſo it is in the gouernment of Chriſt, ſometimes diuiſion and ſtir, ſometimes peace and vnion: we may vſe <hi>Solomons</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this cauſe;
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.2.</note> 
               <hi>All things come alike to all.</hi> Therefore in ſuch variety of times and accidents, it is an vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and groundleſſe affirmation to make peace an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible ſigne of the Church. The Papiſts ſay and in ſome ſort truly,
<note place="margin">Iohn 10.16.</note> we are all called <hi>members of one body vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one head Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 12. And by our Sauiour, <hi>One Shepheard, and one ſheepfold,</hi> therefore diuerſity of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth argue a falſe profeſſion. True indeede in the true members of Chriſts elected congregation, but in the outward fellowſhip and face of an viſible multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3229:13"/>not euer true, where many are among vs that are not of vs the Apoſtle ſaith. In that one ſheepfold where Chriſt was Shepheard, was not one <hi>Iudas</hi> found who had warre and treaſon in his heart and turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Maſter? yet could the chiefe Prieſts, and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, and Pylate agree well enough in murdering him without traitors among themſelues. Outward peace to keepe conformity with others is not in the power of any, but this approcheth neereſt to the truth, the true members of Chriſt are peacable, and full of charitie, and being linked vnder one head by faith doe accord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues: but God ſetteth neere them enemies that loue not peace euen of their owne, to be as thornes in their ſides, and to raiſe them from temporall ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. <hi>Harding</hi> complaines that before <hi>Luther</hi> came, the people were <hi>vnanimes in dome</hi> of one minde in the houſe, but ſince how many diuiſions haue happened? Concerning their ſpirituall conſent in ſuperſtition I will vſe the phraſe of the Text, <hi>The ſtrong man armed kept his Palace and his goods were in peace. Sarcerius</hi> an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitor maketh it a particular inſtance, <hi>Qualia tempora fuerunt ſub Papatu,</hi> Of this ſort were the Popiſh times. May we ſpeake of outward peace and temporall, and not find theſe accuſers faulty? Chriſtianity will haue this peace kept with Alients, as an argument of the minde bent to vnitie; that we may be mercifull as our heauenly Father is mercifull and kind to all: that the glory of a quiet and peacable minde may ſhine forth to confound the cenſures of each ill willervnto Sion. If by this kind of coniecturing, or rather demonſtration; an equall iudge may giue ſentence: ſee whoſe fingers haue beene oftneſt in treaſons; whoſe practiſes haue beene maſſacres; who they are that ſtirre euery cole to fire the ſtates of the world and to raiſe combuſtion. This kind of peace as it hath beene hardly ſeene towards vs, but when neceſſity made them quiet, and God by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence tied their hands &amp; confounded their deuiſes, ſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3229:14"/>hath it beene a ſtranger among them that talke of peace. To reuiue their vnquietnes by relation, or ſhew their diſſentions out of ſtories would ſooner want time then matter. Or to obſerue diſtractions in the head, the chooſing of one Pope againſt another, and the Church at the ſame time vnder more heads then one. Whatſoeuer the ſheepe were ſurely then there was not one ſhepheard. The bones they haue caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Princes that out of their diſſentions they might bring their owne ends about, cannot be vnknowne to him that knoweth any thing. From whence we iuſtly may collect, the head ſet vp for vnity did plot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreement, he was not here what he did profeſſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther led the members by a Chriſtian-like direction. If to ſet iarres and prey vpon the flocke be no good ſigne of a true ſhepheard, this note of vnity is a poore ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication for them.
<note place="margin">Bell. prefat. in lib. de Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Pontifice.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth plainly confeſſe that this ſtate hath beene ſo ſhaken with enemies, and bad liues of the Popes, as alſo with grieuous Schiſme: that for the glory of it, it ſtands not by it ſelfe, but ſtrangely ſupported by diuine preſeruation manifeſted in their infirmity. Indeed it often happeneth by a <hi>Syncretiſmus</hi> as the ancients cald it, that in bred hatred and diſſention weareth out by an enemie abroad, ſo policy (which the children of this world haue) maketh ſtates and humors otherwiſe differing among them to accord: leſt their walls which beganne to ſhake ſhould fall downe quite, if they kept not cloſe together. To this cauſe they haue a ſecond helpe, to muſſle mens mouths, and fetter their conſciences, that in ſome places none may diſpute; the Scripture which perhaps would raiſe ſtirre enough may not be read; they will keepe peace though by taking away Gods weapon. A guilty conſcience is betrayed in this, when all aduentures of triall in theſe conflicts are ſo debard: and like it is if they had giuen ſo much liberty to their owne, as we haue giuen both them and ours: their remainder had beene grieuouſly impoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3229:14"/>and brought to a ſmaller quantity by this time. As for our writings that turne the word of God ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king more generally into particular application, they are affraid at their lookes, neither can indure they ſhould come to a publique view. Then which argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fetchd from their depth of their miſdoubting conſcience, no teſtimonie againſt them can be greater. Their feares are more then <hi>Panike,</hi> moued by great oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, Gods word directed aright, is like the firy tongues wherein the holy Ghoſt did ſit vpon the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which tongues were diuided: being a fire to burne vp the hay and ſtubble of falſe tradition, and like enough to make a diuiſion, whereof they complaine ſo grieuouſly. The ſpirit in them commeth like that mighty wind which fild the houſe wherein the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly was gathered: But as antiquity fained of <hi>Aeolus,</hi> he kept the windes vnder huge Mountaines leaſt all ſhould be ouerturned. And the great commander of heauen and earth deputed an inferiour Lord to rule them.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Regemque dedit qui ſaedere cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Et premere, &amp; laxas ſciret dare iuſſus habenas.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That King was appointed to ſtint their vnrulines: ſo is the diuine word by a counterfeit ſhew of a diuine authoritie to be kept vnder: and he below to play faſt and looſe, expounding all after his owne law and counſell. Thus the candle being put vnder a buſhell (as a darke night ſometimes preuents a skirmiſh) may keepe men from quarelſome proteſtations. Vpon theſe termes their peace ſtandeth, and they are forced to hold with both hands leaſt it ouergoe them <hi>Zanchie</hi> relateth a decree made in Italy,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 8. <hi>de ſcriptura. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in cap.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Titum.</hi>
               </note> the Scripture is permitted to be read of the better ſort, onely with condition that they expound nothing but with the Church of Rome. <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Eſpenceus</hi> one of their owne, reports that an Italian Biſhop told him, that learned men in Italy were affraid
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3229:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſtudy the Scriptures, leaſt by them they might be drawne into hereſie: and they rather imployed their time vpon the Popes law bookes and the decretals. A franciſcan Fryer plainely ſaid the Councell of Trent, the Lutherans did preuaile vpon none ſo much as them which were exerciſed in the Scripture. To ſhew what tyranny keepes their affaires in peace obſerue one proofe inſted of many. <hi>Zanchie</hi> relateth it in his booke <hi>de Eccleſia,</hi> One of the Regular Canons wrot a booke, in which he prooueth the Pope may be called into queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and cenſured by the Church, the reaſon is becauſe he is our brother, and Chriſt ſaith, If thy brother of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee tell the Church. That he is our brother hee prooueth, for in ſaying the Lords prayer he calleth God father: if then all be children in reſpect of God they muſt be brethren among themſelues. The booke for this fault was cald in, an excommunication was ſent out, and the Authour had a checke: yet was the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo ſtrong, that none could anſwere it ſo well as one Courtier, who wiſht his holines neuer to ſay our Father, ſo by not acknowledging a ſuperiour with that Title he might put his greatnes out of queſtion. So ſtrange a ſlauery is produced by this vſurped power, that an eminence and prorogatiue muſt be claimed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the nature of man, and the qualitie of a ſinfull crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and a point of beleefe and conſcience made not to mooue in it any queſtion. By ignorance then is the peace grounded and maintaind by tyranny, not eaſie to be diſcernd whether more barbarous or ridiculous. Well wereit if we could learne wit by their example, that euery ignorant inuention did not forge out a new conceit againſt the preſent times. Or that ſome craſie and miſalledging braines, ſoothed vp by an in bred cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſitie, did not ſo much ſleight antiquitie and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as not care what is generally eſtabliſhed, and hath bene vſed many ages in the Church: euen in the purer time before corruption. For vpon any diſſention,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3229:15"/>thoughts in a ceremonie or ſmall ordinance, we know what complaint the aduerſarie raiſeth. Moreouer a ſmall controuerſie in a branch, depends vpon a roote, and adhereth to ſome queſtion of great moment, the ſame principles in diſputation againſt an indifferent ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie if they ſhould take place: will ouerthrow whole frames of gouernment. But to come to the laſt blow with our aduerſaries. Let truth be wayed in an euen ballance, though quarrelers ſee not their owne blemiſhes ſo directly as they eſpy anothers, peace is no ſuch vniuerſall bleſſing among them. All of them or at leaſt the more ſober ſort allow not the Ieſuits practiſes and poſitions. In free will and predeſtination the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicans &amp; the Ieſuits conſent not, nor the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Franciſcans about the originall ſinne of the Virgine <hi>Mary:</hi> to omit the ſcruples of <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> with their followers in more ſubtile matters. That of the Virgine <hi>Maries</hi> freedome from originall ſinne, was ſo hotly defended by both parties, that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent durſt not decide it for feare of a Schiſme. Where knowledge doth abound, and men haue liberty to ſpeake, the corruption of many will abuſe it. <hi>Nec per ſe mala eſt eruditio, ſed plerumque gignit factiones &amp; diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> ſaith <hi>Eraſmus:</hi> learning is not euill in it ſelfe, but for the moſt part it ingendereth factions and diuiſion. If knowledge then haue a freer paſſage for all ſorts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, their peace hath ſome aduantage. Beſides when a reformation is publiſhed, all cannot haue one conſent in clearing things of moment, hid before and now come to more open light. And if among ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that imbrace the reformed religion, good and bad, wiſe and fooliſh, ſober and curious had all conſented; it had beene a ſigne of falſe Doctrine rather then true: for tares ſpring vp with wheate, and God ioyneth ſome corrections with his bleſſings, weeds may grow alone ſometimes, and heere our Sauiour ſpeaketh of the deuill, and maketh it one part of his ſtrength, His
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3229:16"/>goods are in peace. But ſee the face of former times, did not ſome ſay at firſt I am of <hi>Pauls,</hi> I am of <hi>Apollos,</hi> and others of <hi>Cephas:</hi> a new Doctrine came vp, and ignorant people could not keepe a ſober courſe in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining it. As for the groſſeſt deuiſers among vs, they are partly ſcattered and ſuppreſt, but if we ſpeake of ſetled Churches, ſee worſe then we haue had. The Corinthians doubted of the reſurrection. The Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians called for the ceremonies of the law ſo ſtiffly, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> feared his labour had beene loſt. This one opinion of retaining ceremonies is called by <hi>Muſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus perpetuum certamen</hi> an euerlaſting contention of thoſe times: And the Apoſtles were enforced to call a generall Councell at Ieruſalem to take it vp, and yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſome infirmities for a time forbade eating of blood a thing in it ſelfe indifferent.
<note place="margin">Reu. 2.6.</note> Then came in <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> with his deuiſes, and the ſect of the <hi>Nicolaitans</hi> which God hated. <hi>Ebion</hi> and <hi>Cerinthus</hi> denying the eternall God-head of Chriſt are ſuppoſed to haue giuen occaſion to S. <hi>Iohn</hi> to write his Goſpell. All this while we find not among the Heathen any notorious brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches about the principles of their idolatry. After this when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had giuen peace to the Church, and men might vſe more liberty: the Arrians their ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors ouerflowed in ſuch a number, that it was ſayd of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> their ſtrong oppoſer and a great defender of the truth. <hi>He againſt all the world, and all the world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</hi> This is the decree of God, and therefore his great wiſdome, that by bandying the truth to and fro the ſubſtance of it might be gotten out at laſt, and others raiſed by the aduerſary from ſloth to ſearch it, to make it ſhine more clearely as gold in the furnace, and praiſe him that keepeth it ſafe in ſo many haſards. And if we will make the beſt of a bad matter, we may ſay and not altogether vntruly, we are beholden to Heretiques for a great part of the truth: for they haue ſtird vp the pens of the learned, and occaſioned the holy decrees of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3229:16"/>faithfull and religious Councels. To conclude this point. Arguments from peace and conſent, are no certaine or demonſtratiue proofe either of a good or a bad cauſe: Peace among Saints vnder Chriſt as we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it in the minde, is a ſpirituall vertue: as we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it a beautifull ornament, or ſweete harmony, when multitudes are coupled in a bond of happy ſociety, it is a temporall bleſſing, for ſpirituall things are in the minde. Matters of this quality doe ebbe and flow, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times giuen, and ſometimes taken away from the Church. When Gods heritage tranſgreſſeth, breaches are often made, and his owne ſcourged moſt ſeuerely. <hi>Dauid</hi> a man neereſt him is extreamely threatned after his offence, <hi>The ſword ſhall neuer depart from thy houſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.10.</note> although he was ſo iuſt and penitent, with his raigne ſo happy and flouriſhing. Euery Church hath in it both good and bad, therefore no peace can continue long without ſome impediment. Our Sauiour ſaith, I came not to ſend peace into the world but a ſword, this was the reaſon, ſome would imbrace him and others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe: ſo father would be againſt ſonne, and ſonne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt father, and a mans enemies would be they of his owne houſhold. S. <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe affirmeth,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.19.</note> 
               <hi>There muſt be hereſies among you that they which are approoued may be made manifest.</hi> the light and fantaſticall head to vaine deuiſes fit for him, and the iuſt againſt him to manifeſt himſelfe, and expreſſe his gifts in maintaining the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect truth. The deuill as he vſeth doth imitate God in part, though in another intent, ſometime he ſetteth diſſention among his owne, yet warreth not againſt himſelfe, though his be diuided, he is not. For this is the difference betweene his poſſeſſion and others, hee keepeth his palace not to defend but to deſtroy it, and if diſſention fit his purpoſe, hee can ſcourge his owne with this rod, to pleaſe himſelfe in their torment. But when occaſion requireth vnity, he will not deuide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelfe, but keepeth this forces whole to doe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3229:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>greater miſchiefe, as <hi>Herode</hi> and <hi>Pylate</hi> enemies before were reconciled at the death of Chriſt: and brethren in euill communicate their counſels. This maketh him ſtronger, and keepeth his palace in greater ſecurity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>His goods are in peace.</hi> Hitherto of the vſurped power.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part followeth; the lawfull power, firſt the victory, <hi>When a ſtronger then be ſhall come vpon him and ouercome him.</hi> The particle but noteth a coherence, we muſt looke for ſome thing beſides the words. Conſider it then as the branch of an argument. He is the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that ouer commeth, but plain it is he yeeldeth to my command: therefore aſcribe ſtrength vnto me. The Papiſts vſe this argument to confirme their exerciſing and adiuring the deuill, and from the fucceſſe of their words ſtriue to iuſtifie a counterfeit miracle, becauſe ſometime he goeth backe, and ſeemeth to yeeld to their holy water, and the ſigne of the Croſſe. We anſwere the deuill doth delude them, that by leauing the body he may poſſeſſe the ſoule, and eſtabliſh ſuperſtition. They reply, and ſay this is the Phariſees anſwere, who ſayd caſting out and diſpoſſeſſion was by couenant and compact: and did not approue the ſtronger man by his worke. But this is inſufficient, for the Phariſees ſayd Chriſt was not ſtrong enough to worke theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of himſelfe, but Satan was diuided, and gaue him helpe: we call not the ſtrength of Chriſt into queſtion. As for the aduerſary he diſſenteth not from his owne party, but ſeemeth to fly that by a ſtrategem he might deceiue them. Secondly, Antichriſt doth worke ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wonders, the Scripture doth prophecy as much, but no lying wonder can be without ſhow of a true and mighty operation: therefore they muſt worke mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles with ſome notable point of diſſembling. Chriſt had power to cure diſeaſes as well as to diſpoſſeſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirits, his miracles were beyond all exception: one did helpe to confirme another, and both ioyned to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3229:17"/>confirme his Doctrine. Heerein they faile: They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe as Chriſt did, heale diſeaſes: therefore their halting betraies their lameneſſe, and we may ſuſpect their dealings are vnſound. Thirdly, ſome of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles are forged, all the world knows it wel: if then the viewing of them may helpe our iudgementin eſteeming theſe, they come both from one Fountaine, for truth and falſe-hoode haue no fellowſhip. To diſſemble and giue out is great policy ſometimes, and we know they deale with a great politician, who may not refuſe to looſe a little for the gaining of more: as in Magicke he is content to ſubiect himſelfe, as if words could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand him, which cannot be done indeede: but this counterfeit ſeruice maketh him a maſter, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander that calleth him the greater ſlaue. In the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church when miracles did laſt, this exorciſing had a diuine power, for which there was great reaſon, ſeeing in ſo dangerous a time the Infidels did worſhip theſe powers of darkneſſe. Chriſt gaue his followers a gift to ſhew the truth and ſtrength of his profeſſion, for to encourage his owne, and conuert the obſtinate mindes of others. <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſpeaketh of the efficacy thereof in this manner.
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Diu. inftit.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>Cuius nomine adiurati corpori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus excedunt, quorum verbis tanquam flagris verberati: non modo daemonas ſe eſſe confitentur, ſed etiam nomina ſua edunt.</hi> Being adiured by the name of Chriſt they goe out of bodies, by words as whips they are beaten and tormented, and doe not onely confeſſe they ate deuils, but tell their names. Likewiſe <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his booke to <hi>Demetrianus,</hi> the Chriſtians great enemie, telleth him what kind of Gods he worſhipped. <hi>O ſi audire eos vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, &amp;c.</hi> O that thou wouldeſt heare them, when they are adiured by our ſpirituall ſtripes, and our tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting words, are caſt out of poſſeſſed bodies, feeling the power of God, and confeſſing the iudgment to come. Theſe were teſtimonies of Chriſt the ſtronger man, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all power in Heauen and Earth ſubiect to his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3229:18"/>word. Some ſuppoſe that as a teſtimonie of Chriſts victorie ouer him, he cannot come to Heauen as hee did before the incarnation. In the old teſtament when the Angels came before the Lord, a ſpirit came to offer his ſeruice to ſeduce King <hi>Achab:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kings 22.21.</note> and make him fall before his enemies in the battell. And when the children of God ſtood before his preſence, Satan was among them, <hi>Iob.</hi> 1. But they ſuppoſe he cannot come thither any more ſince Chriſt aſcended vpin perſon, and to that purpoſe alledge the place, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.18. <hi>I ſaw Satan as lightening fall from heauen, and</hi> Reu. 12.9. <hi>Michael expeld the Dragon from thence with his Angels, their place was no more found in heauen, the old Serpent that deceiueth the world was caſt out into the earth, and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels with him:</hi> and therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth him <hi>Prince of the power of the Aire,</hi> becauſe his ruling is confined within that ſpace, he can goe no higher. Theſe are a vouched with great probability. But ſure it is, Chriſt ſhooke his Kingdome in the earth, being borne and ſent into the world to deſtroy his workes: that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which ſate in darkeneſſe before might ſee great light, and they be deliuered which ſate in the region and ſhaddow of death. As light which ſhines from heauen is diffuſed (nothing in nature hauing a power to ſpread it ſelfe more ſuddenly) illuſtrating the whole Hemiſphere or halfe at once: ſo did this Sonne of righteouſneſſe, as was ſayd, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. <hi>Nothing was hid from the heat thereof:</hi> but beyond the regions of Iury, his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles carried it farre and wide into many Nations. This was the ſtronger hand of this Conquerour, that by a people ſcorned as for ſuperſtition by others, and then torne by the Romanes, being the weaker ſide: he gaue lawes vnto the mighty, and caſt him out of the world then ſtrongly poſſeſt, and kept as his owne houſe in ſinne and ignorance. The Oracles were put downe after his incarnation, where the deuill had long time giuen aduiſe and anſweres. <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> inquiring
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3229:18"/>at <hi>Delphes</hi> who ſhould ſucceede him in the Empire, had this for an anſwere.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Peucerus de Oraculis, pag.</hi> 251.</note>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>An Hebrew childe, King of the Gods, hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me to leaue this houſe and returne to hell: therefore henceforth forſake our Altars. And hee is bound for a thouſand yeares, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 20. Which we may take from the riſing of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> vntill the raigne of <hi>Otoman,</hi> or howſoeuer; in that ſpace Chriſt did greatly confound his Kingdome, and ſet vp his owne: The ſucceſſe we haue ſeene, our Sauiours victory, to open it more fully, note the perſon called the ſtronger Man, and the meanes vſed to ſubdue him.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is God, equall with the Father, his ſtrength is in the World, and beyond, it euery way infinite. God is Almighty, this attribute is prefixed before other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles in the beginning of the Creed, for in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil any beleeue but one able and potent, leaſt his confidence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him. Might then maketh way to all beleefe, and beleefe to all performances, for <hi>Faith ouercommeth the world ſaith S. Iohn.</hi> He is called <hi>the Lord of Hoſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn 5.4.</note> all power being his army. Let men muſter, plot, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour neuer ſo much: this power commandeth them and theirs, the ſtrength of this huge World is to him but as an arrow in the hand of a Gyant, aimed and ſhot forth by his owne direction. The ſpirituall powers are to miniſter and ſerue in their ſtations, ready to attend and execute his precepts. And if one Angell made ſuch a ſlaughter in <hi>Senacheribs</hi> army in one night, what was the power of him that ſent him. Diuine ſtrength as it animateth faith, ſo is it the ground of all religion. Men are made to reuerence it, and the end of all acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is to acknowledge: and nothing is more diſtaſted by the Almighty God, then to ſee arrogant preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3229:19"/>or negligent obſeruance admire ſtrength any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way. Weake creatures liue by it, and the name of a creature hath it ingrauen as the proper ſtampe. To vſe the Prophets words, ſhall the ſtrong man glory in his ſtrength? or the wiſe man in his wiſdome? or the rich man in his wealth? or any man in any thing, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the earth is weake and the inhabitants therein, hee beareth vp the Pillars of it. Is any good expected? Hope for it hence. Is any enioyed? Giue glory to the founder, all is receiued from this fulnes. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 68. <hi>ver.</hi> 34. <hi>Aſcribe yee ſtrength vnto God, his excellencie is ouer Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrael, and his ſtrength is the Clouds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Euery good thing is but a gift, and giuing can onely make it proſper: greateſt hopes doe ſometimes breake in the middeſt, becauſe the receiuers of fruit reſpect not the Tree whence they fall. They looke at their owne beginnings, and at their owne ends, and their courſes in the proceeding attend their owne deſires. And though this ſtrength might ſay vnto the foole deale not ſo madly, and to the vngodly ſet not vp your horne: though promotion come neither from the Eaſt, nor the Weſt, nor from the South: a dull deſire cannot look ſo high as heauen, neither acknowledgeth any ruler but one who leadeth by common ſenſe. Hee will ſleepe at a Sermon, that can wake at the diſcourſe of a commodity: or a miſhap can keepe from ſleeping. And ſleight the ſtrict aduiſe of Scripture; when the words of a great man in politique reſpect make him double diligent. Generally inbuſineſſe of moment (though liuing being and moouing be from God) who will not more cheerefully rely vpon friends and ſtrong helpers, then on Gods furtherance and promiſed aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? By this ſtrength vnlikely matters haue come to paſſe moſt vſually, great imaginations haue beene diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with a blaſt, dying hopes haue beene reuiued from the graue: all which proclaime an vnconquered and inſcrutable power of the Lord in working; not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3229:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>by raſh cenſurers, but eaſily diſcerned by the iudgement of truth. Euen when vngodlineſſe is grownelofty, it either falleth of it ſelfe, or by the puſh of a like aduerſary is caſt vnder foot; all ſtrength we ſee wearing out, and this force of Diuine power breaking downe the gate that will not open, that howſoeuer the beginnings goe, at laſt the ſtronger man will ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. From hence let euery proſuming enemie bee danted, though fortified in his wickednes. Let euery wearied ſeruant be encouraged, to paſſe euen through the valley of the ſhaddow of death and feare no euill. <hi>Iob</hi> had complained, and his vncomfortable friends made him ſometimes bitter, at laſt the Lord did chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge him to anſwere, and cald him hither.
<note place="margin">Iob 38.4.</note> 
               <hi>Where waſt thou when I layd the foundations of the Earth, when I ſhut vp the Sea with doores. Haſt thou commanded the morning ſince thy daies, and cauſed the day ſpring to know his place? Nabuchodonoſor,</hi> in the height of his arrogance boaſted of his great Palace, and building: but for his labour had an ill reward, he was made fellow with the beaſts of the field,
<note place="margin">Dan. 4.25.</note> 
               <hi>Till he knew the moſt High ruled in the Kingdome of men, and gaue it to whom he would.</hi> S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſeeing Chriſt vnder the burthen of our ſinnes, laying a ſide his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and ready to be apprehended, went out of the way to helpe him, and wounded one of the high Prieſts ſeruants. This perſwaſion called him into a right frame. <hi>Thinkeſt thou that I cannot pray to my Father,
<note place="margin">Matth. 26.58.</note> and he ſhall preſently giue me more then twelue legions of Angels.</hi> This one ground-worke of true obedience made <hi>Iob</hi> know his vilenes, the lofty tyrant his weaknes, the zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Diſciple his due compaſſe: as generall patternes vnto all, to limite their extrauagant humours, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are to keepe within their bounds. That neither the complaint of natures weakenes ſhould vrge diſtruſt in neceſſity; nor preſumption ſwell in windy ſhowes, nor buſie attempting meddle beyond the rule of Gods direction. Weake is that ſtrength which his arme doth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3229:20"/>not ſupport, and ſtrong are thoſe endeauours hee bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, though full of weakeneſſe.</p>
            <p>We haue ſeene the ſtronger man, able to ouercome by power and greatnes: now ſee the way of conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and the ſtrength deſtroyd that lay againſt him. All know his force is infinite, but by what conueiance this vertue is expreſt, and frames the Creature, is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: who can trace the footſteps? <hi>Semper agens &amp; ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per quietus,</hi> as <hi>Auſten</hi> ſpeaketh, alwaies working, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies quiet. He worketh without change, without la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour or any difficulty. To ſpeake the neereſt to truth is to ſpeake the greateſt, his will is his worke, his word his law, he commanded and they were created. Among men words being of ſmall worth are ſayd to be but winde, their labours muſt toile a little in effecting things of moment: but God decreeth, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture reduceth all to his word, which executeth his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: By this effectuall meanes all are brought about, and that by a double word, to which hell and Satan and all his enemies yeeld. The word whoſe ſound we heare to teach vs, and his word of prouidence whereby he ſuſtaineth vs, whereof the enemy maketh confeſſion <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Man ſhall not liue by bread alone but by euery word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God.</hi> The firſt rules within, the ſecond without: and one goeth along with the other to iudge and correct the Worlds courſes.</p>
            <p>The firſt commeth and ouercommeth, <hi>It is the power of God to ſaluation, Rom.</hi> 1.16. If that power excelleth all which goeth beyond all, nothing can equall it. It ſubdueth the minde, and comming into the boſome medleth with a mans ſecrets, with an inuiſible controll. It worketh vpon tyrants themſelues, and pierceth into that place where neither tyranny nor the whole earth can get an entrance. It bringeth euery high thought into captiuity, and the proudeſt is brought vpon his knees in loweſt ſubmiſſion if hee once be ſenſible of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3229:20"/>himſelfe. <hi>The word of God is quicke, and powerfull and ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per then any two edged ſword, piercing euen to the deuiding aſſunder of the ſoule and ſpirit: and of the ioynts and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts, and intents of the heart, Heb.</hi> 4.12. Strong in ſucceſſe, when God giueth his commandement vpon the Earth it runneth ſwiftly: and nothing can ſtop, or caſt impediments ſufficient in the way. Compared for that end to leauen, hid in three meaſures of meale till the whole was leauened: to muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard-ſeede a little graine, yet caſt into a garden grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into a great Tree, and the foules of the Aire are lodged in the branches. Vpon ſmall and poore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings it hath taken ſuch roote, and fixed it ſelfe where it got poſſeſſion, that no Dominion hath beene larger.</p>
            <p>It was at firſt, and ſhall be laſt, though people fall and Kingdomes like to Kings haue their periode. Though nations looſe it, and where the day is gone before the night may be expected: though perſecution hath made it almoſt inuiſible: yet hath the Sunne riſen againe, or ſhined in another place, it hath beene raiſed vp againſt the hope of ill willers, and beyond the reach of humane wiſdome and worldly helpers. This word expelleth Satan, and as by ſaying the word the deuills obeyed and the poſſeſſed were ſet free: ſo are ſinfull hearts gained out of thraldome, by him that came to preach deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to the captiues, and to ſet the bruiſed at liberty. But one may thinke where is this power if we iudge by the ſucceſſe, ſo many hearts continue flinty in their ſinnes, as if the ſpirituall weapon wanted power, or the ſtrong man truſting in his Armour were able to beare of the blow. Good fellowſhip can ſometimes waſh away the ſtrokes it giueth, bad example can ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>match it beyond compariſon: and cuſtome can ſeare the conſcience, that often hearing careth not if repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion beate againe, and againe vpon a knowne fault. Beſides it ſauours of ſimplicity, teacheth a man to deny
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3229:21"/>himſelfe, to take vp the croſſe, to turne out of his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued way, and repent: that the Pillars of ſtrength and policy are here defectiue: and in their roome all points of infirmity.</p>
            <p>Theſe manifold ſuppoſed wants that ariſe from the ill ſpeeding, may haue an anſwere branching out into equall diuerſities: for this ſtrength is not alwaies ſeene, nor alwaies working. If God ſhould let his power and iudgements dwell vpon the conſcience of euery repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate minde, confuſion would fill all places. Many hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers are condemned and made euill by the ſtrength of the Word, one that hath no reſolution to amend, in hearing taketh truth by the halfe, and ſnatcheth ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to his purpoſe. When he heareth of Gods mercy there is an occaſion to preſume: or of iudgement, when he ſeeth not the effect at firſt, there is an occaſion of doubt, of negligence, and deferring. The Law being vnfolded, and ſtrict obedience vrged, giueth occaſion to reiect that ſeruice as a ſeuere taske, or a yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke too tedious to carry. And the word of God is ſtrong ſtill, as phyſicke may be ſtrong though it cannot cure: but account it ſtrong as phyſicke, it either worketh the good or the bad way: either as the ſauour of life vnto life, or the ſauour of death vnto death, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh. Moreouer the word is a ſauing inſtrument, and hath one end and property, for this maketh an inſtrument more perfect, to execute one ſufficient ſeruice and there reſt, ſeeing nature maketh <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, euery thing for a peculiar end, therefore it may want ſome orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and perfections which belongeth to other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances. The weaker it is, if ſtronger effects be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, the principall agent is more commended, and made manifeſt, and for this cauſe God hath kept the glory of all workes to himſelfe, imparting onely ſome portion to the meanes. The word then being an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument is weaker, becauſe it aimeth at one end onely, to make way for iudgement, and not to execute it, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3229:21"/>becauſe it dependeth vpon God the chiefe worker: but in this regard exceeding mighty, becauſe the hand of God goeth with it, ſo it can make no ſhew at all, yet inforce the good and terrifie the bad. As the ſtrongeſt body is weake, and ſtirres not without the ſoule, ſo are words nothing without him that giues-them efficacy from aboue. Shouting and ſound of trumpets were no ſuch engines in military aſſaults; theſe by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment did fell the walls of <hi>Iericho.</hi> And S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth the ſcribe and wiſe man hath no ſhare in this buſines, rather ſhut out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to condemne the wiſe,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.27.</note> and the weake things of the world to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the mighty:</hi> And addeth the reaſon, <hi>that no fleſh might glory in his preſence.</hi> Heerein then conſiſteth the words glory, that going the more vnlikely way to worke, it ſpeedeth, and where it ſpeedeth not, confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on followes immediately. Let any without partiality ſee, by what meane beginnings, againſt what heate of perſecution, the ſtrength of the Lord ſubdued hell, and planted religion by the firſt conuerting of the Gentiles, with the Apoſtles and their followers: it may turne the Atheiſt, and raiſe the moſt dull and frozen ſpirits into admiration. In reforming religion we haue ſeene the like, if the firſt hopes failed, the ſecond haue ſped, and by no power or policy of the earth doth the Goſpell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy proſperity. If any intent of perſecution, or crafty dealing could haue giuen it a deadly wound, the face of it had not beene left to appeare before this time to make ſhow, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the voice of it to ſpeake for it ſelfe. This muſt teach vs to carry a conſtant hope, let the ſtrong man mooue, and his inſtruments thunder out their threatnings, and where they thunder leaſt, colour their cloſe deuiſes to confound all in the end; a vaine expectation muſt be the fruit of ſuch confidence, and their owne confuſion finiſh vp their labour. This rocke cannot remooue, nor the ſtronger ſide fall though it
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3229:22"/>ſuffer many foiles,
<note place="margin">1. Eſdras 4.41.</note> and ſome diſaduantage. Let our concluſion goe with the Apocry phall Hiſtory. Diuers were ſeuerally conceited where was the greateſt ſtrength found, ſome gaue it to Princes, ſome to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and to wine, but truth obtaind it from the reſt, ſhe ſpake for him, that ſpake for her: ſo went the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the King, and the cry of others. <hi>Magnaeſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas &amp; praeualet,</hi> great is the truth and preuaileth. And ſo much for the firſt meanes whereby the ſtronger man ſubdueth, the power of his word.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is his word of prouidence, the mighty voice in operation, at whoſe command all things moue and obey in Heauen and Earth.</p>
            <p>The riſing of ſome, and the falling of others, and in a word the falling of a ſparrow: the cariage of great and ſmall meete in this gouernment. <hi>Solomon</hi> will haue vs know, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.14. <hi>What he purpoſeth ſhall ſtand, to it can no man adde, and from it can none diminiſh; that we might feare before him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But heere his footeſteps are hardly perceiued. The ſtrong Man ſwaieth ſo much, and the worlds behauiour appeareth ſo ſtrange: that his preſence ſeemeth very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, &amp; his Maieſty to keepe retyred and withdrawne. As in the former word of ſauing health, the victory ſtood doubtfull in the eyes of carnall apprehenſion: the caſe is heere the very ſame. <hi>Claudian</hi> guided by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine rules, ſheweth how they gaue him a halting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion betweene contraries, ſo many Eclipſes doth this light ſuffer, ſuch thruſting there is againſt God and godlines, ſuch preuailing of the bad and pride withall: that he meruailed the God of all things ſhould be in the earth, and giue no more proofe of his ſtrength and victory. In theſe termes hee openeth his doubtfull meaning. <hi>When I ſee the glorious frame of Heauen and Earth, the bounds of the Sea, Summer and Winter fitly diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in their ſeaſons, the courſes of day and night ſo orderly to ſucceede: I thought God had giuen theſe lawes by ſingular
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3229:22"/>wiſdome, and adorned his gifts with ſuch diſtinction. But when I ſaw ſuch darkenes vpon the affaires of men, the proud and vngodly flouriſhing, and the innocent vnder foote:</hi> rurſus labefacta cadebat religio, <hi>religion beganne to faile.</hi> Though his owne plaine reaſon did ground him well in part, Yet did a Heatheniſh minde thus plunge him in diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. There is but a haires breadth betweene the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of many Chriſtians, and this mans opinion, if the beſt waies be not proſperous they are forſaken, and howſoeuer men haue a meaning, the double dealing is to common.</p>
            <p>See then on what ground it ſtands: Many times the Lord will not ſhew his might, his enemie gets the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hand, impiety will domineere, no way to croſſe it: where is then this victory mentioned in the Text? It appeareth that this obiection may be forcible, becauſe <hi>Dauid</hi> or the Author of the 73. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> confeſſed that his feete were almoſt gone when he beheld the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of vngodlineſſe.</p>
            <p>But going at laſt into the Sanctuary, hee beheld the ſlippery place of ſuch doubtfull felicity, and found the glory to be but ſmall which a moment can bring to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, or ioy in a dreame that endeth with the night when one awaketh.</p>
            <p>May it not rather amaze the enemie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found vngodlines, when proſperity ſhall be great, that deſtruction may be anſwerable? Nothing can match with his wiſdome, that knoweth how to giue way to folly, that he may plucke downe the power of it being growne ripe, and defeat ſuch aduancement in the height. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> truly ſheweth a great man may not at all times, declare himſelfe, among inferiours, it were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to wreſtle among the weaker, or diſpute among the fooliſh,
<note place="margin">4. Ethic. 3.</note> the world is too weake and baſe to receiue this ſtrength of God in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding the deuill. If the Almighty ſhould ſtriue, what place were left either for good or bad, to finiſh
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3229:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>their owne intentions, or runne out their courſes? If his iuſtice did puniſh euery ſinne who could indure it? if he did reward euery vertue, where were the patience of Saints of glorious in earth, or their reward ſo great in heauen? The world would too much ingroſſe the loues of men, if all things did runne ſmoothly as they would imagine. See how vainely weake deſires ſtriue to fix a reſt in the confines of this preſent State, though ſuch ſmall occaſion be giuen, and the waies thereof fild with garboils and confuſion. Take one that liues in a troubled place, ſuppoſe he be ſicke and diſeaſed in his body, his friends leaue him, or faile in their comforts, and age haſten on the remembrance of his departure: we ſhall often find, the loue of life will make one ſo qualified, to ſticke in this mirie place, and dote vppon theſe tranſitorie ſhaddowes. For this cauſe the Lord ſheweth his ſcourges rather then his benefits, reſeruing the beauty of abſolute gouernment in the full luſtre till another ſeaſon, yet here beginnes and layeth the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of his victory. His workes (although the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and the end cannot be of one forme) want not to an indifferent beholder. Satan and the malice of his inſtruments receiue many a grieuous foile, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of his truth many encouragements, and none ſhall want his ayd that duly craues it. Helpe was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to S. <hi>Paul</hi> when it ſeemed denied, and he buffeted with Satans meſſenger.</p>
            <p>This promiſefaild not,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.9.</note> being a generall ſtay in har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt conflicts: <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee, for my strength is made perfect in weaknes,</hi> So ſtrong is the hand of God where it leaſt appeareth. And this much of Chriſts victory, <hi>But when a ſtronger then he ſhall come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him and ouercome him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now followeth the gaine. <hi>Hee taketh from him all his armour wherein he truſted and deuideth his ſpoiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The deuill truſteth in his armour, as if he preuailed more by mens weakeneſſe, then his owne power, a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3229:23"/>peruerſe cariage is made his furniture: yeeld not your members <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> weapons of vnrighteouſnes, or armes vnto ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.13. Chriſt truſteth not in his armour, but in himſelfe, redeeming by his infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſauing by his grace: Satan wins vpon aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. Chriſt rather againſt aduantage; and aboue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary poſſibility. Hauing conquered his and our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, the next worke is to diſarme the vſurper, and take away his weapon. The body and the ſoule are the prize gained in this conqueſt, firſt poſſeſſed by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer, and made his inſtruments: now gained and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured ſo highly, as to make vp a trophey, to yeeld the Sauiour praiſe and glory. Theſe then are onely happy, being made the ſpoiles of Chriſt, that as ſhields, or any ſpoiles in warre, are kept as monuments to poſterity, ſhe wing forth his worthines that wonne them to after ages: ſo the ſoule and body of one redeemed in glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying God for deliuerance, are made partakers of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and ſaluation: A proofe we haue here of the ſoules worthines, that the Sonne of God refuſed not to enter the liſts of oppoſition for it. It excelleth the whole world, Chriſt ſaith the gaine of the world is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the loſſe of a mans ſoule.
<note place="margin">Matth. 12.29.</note> For as the ſoule is Gods veſſell (for S. <hi>Matthew</hi> vſeth the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſo much) all things are the ſubiects of the ſoule, ſeruing it as ſo many inferiours. Ioy is in heauen for one ſoule gained from the clawes of this ſpirituall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourer. From it proceeds religious worſhip, and from it alone. Die it cannot, ſo it becommeth an euerlaſting heritage, and by conſequence a greater purchaſe. Chriſt taketh this for himſelfe, <hi>Yee were as ſheepe going aſtray but are now returned to the Shepheard and Biſhop of your ſoules.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25. The bodies alſo engaged formerly to the enemy, are partakers in the ranſome. Teſtimonies faile not to giue aſſurance, bleſſings exhibited to the ſoule are ſealed, and conueied by ordinances corporall. The body is waſhed in Baptiſme, fed in his Supper, and to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3229:24"/>be raiſed vp at the laſt day. Our Sauiour ſuffered in both, afflicted in the garden, and fallen into an agonie: and after died for ſinne vpon the Croſſe. As he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he ouercame, and as he ouercame he gained: he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth both, and maketh his conqueſt abſolute. A ſeruant is ſayd to haue his name a <hi>ſeruando</hi> from preſeruing. In warre when they had taken priſoners, they vſed not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, but thoſe whom by law, they might haue kild, by equity they made their ſeruants. Chriſt hauing van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed the ſtrong Man, is become the abſolute Lord. <hi>He taketh from him all his armour wherein he trusteth and deuideth his ſpoiles.</hi> In the meane time, poore man that maketh ſo much eſtimation of himſelfe, ſee what recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God and the truth make of him. Hee whoſe thoughts neuer ceaſe almoſt from domineering, is but anothers vaſſalat the beſt, wonne by the law of Armes, and onely happy in being conquered.</p>
            <p>The Text maketh him yet lower, armour, goods, weapons, ſpoiles and a houſe are things without life, not ſtirring except they be ſtird: to theſe are men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled. We may then well cry out, <hi>I nunc ſuperbe.</hi> Let pride goe on,
<note place="margin">Sen.</note> and ſinfull arrogance weary out it ſelfe in boaſting. Well may this point conclude with this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, the mother of humility, therefore the firſt ſtep to grace.</p>
            <p>All are but inſtruments, either vnder a good or a bad agent; as goods are onely good for vſe, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons put of and on at anothers pleaſure. <hi>Tully</hi> ſayd of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> the common-wealth ſhould make vſe of him but no further, onely to deſtroy a contrary faction <hi>Marke Antony</hi> and his adhaerents, <hi>ornandus laudandus tollendus,</hi> he was to be praiſed, cheriſhed, and after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued out of the way: ſo are all men, though with great difference but for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> turne, if they ſuruay iuſtly their owne abilities. God may ſay to the beſt as he did to them that bare the burden and the heate of the day, may not I doe with mine owne what I liſt, and as the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3229:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Prophet in alike buſines, <hi>Let not the axe boaſt againſt him that heweth with it. Eſay,</hi> 10.15. Bleſſednes is their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for they fight vnder his Banner, yet not of their owne chuſing, their wayes are inſtrumentall. But of all other a wicked man hath ſmall cauſe to triumph, where the enemy is his leader, and although no counſell can tame him, this one meditation might coole his courage. If ſome tormentor of the Common-wealth did conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that onely by Gods permiſſion, and the deuils in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation he may or muſt be a plague to inferiours for a time, becauſe of the vncharitablenes of men, of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes, ſacriledge, and ſuch incurable ſinnes: to take that by rapine, which will be got to no good vſes. If the ambitious climber did ſuppoſe, God gaue ſome way to his humours, and if hee ſerues not him that ſet him vp, he ſhall neuertheleſſe find true theſe words of <hi>Cyprian, Cui plus dignitatis aſcribitur ab eoplus exigetur ſeruitutis,</hi> to whom God alotteth the greateſt dignity he requires from him greateſt ſeruice: that either a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine will come heere, or at laſt a worſe fire then <hi>Phaeton</hi> had, if his chariot keepe not a right courſe.</p>
            <p>If the voluptuous <hi>Libertine</hi> did conſider, though God may let him inioy his delicacy with content, finding him good for nothing elſe, hating inſtruction and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for Diſcipline, but the end is to fat him againſt the day of ſlaughter, that all theſe are giuen vp as ſlaues, to him that will correct them as ſlaues hereafter, if it did not amend them, it might amaze them in their bad proceedings.</p>
            <p>But to conclude the point with, the greate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality, we muſt account all but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpoiles, inſtruments, and anothers poſſeſſion. We may read the characters of obedience in the face of the whole Earth, and the ſtate thereof framed by prouidence to ſubiection, and euery degree of men appointed to ſome ſeruice. The meaner ſort ſubiect to the greater, ſtirre not without them, and the greater ſtand not without
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3229:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>the meaner. God hath linked one with the other to bridle both, and they either agree or diſagree as he in mercy or iudgement ſhall appoint. Particular orders ſhew the like, euery ſonne ſubiected to his parent, euery ſeruant to his maſter, all Nobility to the Prince, and he to God, and all theſe by carefull prouiſion: as the Sonne of man came not to be ſerued but to ſerue, and as the Apoſtle counſelleth, let him that hath an office waite vpon his office. That I may call the whole world as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> doth a ſeruant, <hi>inſtrumentum animatum,</hi> a liuing inſtrument: the great dealers in it are leaſt of all them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, the more they are, the greater their debt, the more they ſtirre, the more they are led and wrought vpon. And ſo much of the ſecond part of the Text; our Sauiours power. A compendious diſpatch ſhall ſoone finiſh the laſt, which containeth a vſe for his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditours.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he ſtrike that negligence, <hi>He that is not with me is againſt me.</hi> There are Neutralls in the world, ſome it ſeemed at that time, ſtood ſtedfaſt neither with Chriſt, nor the Phariſees: they gaue both the hearing, but did according to their owne pleaſures, to ſhew it were no newes, if after times, and perhaps theſe of ours ſwarme with a like company. But if ſome ſtay betweene good and bad, how doe theſe words comprehend all vnder good and bad, admitting none of a middle ranke. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">Pſalme 69.28</note> as the Pſalmiſt did pray that his enemies might be blotted out of the Booke of the liuing, when in very truth they were neuer written there, for then their names could not haue beene raced out: onely in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming hypocriſie they had written themſelues there, therefore he prayeth God would renounce them open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and proue them to be none of his: ſo is it here, no Neutralls but in opinion, others may thinke them ſo, or they themſelues, but Chriſt flatly diſcardeth all ſuch. <hi>Hee that is not with me is againſt me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We neede not with S. <hi>Ieromie</hi> expound it of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3229:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>in particularly, but including others with him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre it to thoſe idle hearers, which heard his words, and ſaw miracles to no purpoſe, &amp; ſo were enemies. <hi>Quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis non adiuuat quodammodoſe opponit</hi> ſaith <hi>Caluin,</hi> hee that doth not helpe, appoſeth in a ſort, ſuch negligence maketh the enemies more arrogant, and the well wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers more diſcouraged: euen in humane affaires a man is more open for his enemies to play vppon, if his friends faile him, then if he had not any. And what greater enemic hath religion then deuotion without practiſe: this maketh all the world ſuperficiall, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons heard like orations, the vehemency of Gods command is let ſlip, and this made a buſines of the eare. And when faults are commonly taxed, the hearers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count all but a worneſubiect, and a beaten theame, whereby the word is become as ſounding braſſe, or emptie crackes to no end: ſo theſe indifferent friends turne grieuous aduerſaries.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 1. <hi>de peccatorum meritis,</hi> 28.</note> Let vs thinke with S. <hi>Auſten nec eſt vlli vllus medins locus, vt poſſit eſſe niſi cum diabolo qui non eſt cum Chriſto.</hi> There is no middle place for any, he muſt needs be with the deuill that is not with Chriſt. If then we be not Chriſts enemies, we muſt doe two things that we may be with him, maintaine his cauſe when wee ſee his commandement: and <hi>vindicate</hi> his honour, if any diſgrace his words and offend him. By the firſt we make confeſſion of our faith vpon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſpeake his truth and practiſe it, ſo we honour him as his followers, ſaue our ſelues by the right courſe, and gaine others to him by example. This benefit is great. Many ſtand with him, that many doe ſtand for: And example becauſe it beateth vpon the ſences, by an open Oratory proues the ſtrongeſt mouer. As among plants that grow, the ſeede lyeth in the fruit: ſo the fruit of a godly life is as ſeed, it propagateth religion, and ſtirreth vp others to godlines. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Let yourlight ſhine before men.</hi> S. <hi>Auſten</hi> reaſoneth why?
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.14.</note> ſeeing elſe where he commandeth good workes ſhould be done in ſecret,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3229:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>and anſwereth, not that any ſhould praiſe you but <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſi fiant, quod eſt,</hi> may glorifie your Father which is in heauen, and become worſhippers of him by your exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Secondly, we muſt reproue ſinne, <hi>vindicate</hi> his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, account his enemies (conſidering their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) our owne. Nothing is more defaced then godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, one reaſon whereof is this, men ſufferit to reſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely vnder their noſe, and where ſinne is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trold it waxeth ſhameleſſe. The Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> foretold of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Eſay 53.2.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhould grow vp as a tender plant, and as a roote out of a dry ground,</hi> the world ſhould yeeld him ſmall moiſtures, and his truth would be bended and bowed like a tender ſprig of ſmall account. One complained of nature, that man the beſt creature was brought into the world weakeſt, naked, deſtitute, and vnable to help himſelfe. So fareth it with the beſt cauſe of truth and honeſty, hauing plaine dealing for a companion, when vice is armed, and wants not the fence of a guardian and protector. The earth is become a ſtage, and the cheefe actors egregious hypocrites, it yeelds the ſhow of ſoundnes when the inward ſubſtance is rotten, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending much and performing little. Men will fight rather <hi>pro focis</hi> then <hi>pro aris,</hi> for their priuate reſpects, then Gods glory. Perhaps a religious cauſe may haue defenders, but if it be oppoſed, or procure hatred, and croſſe other mens humours, that once it become a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den or a charge, they caſt it off, though they looſe Chriſt and all by the departure. They follow ſinne with the ſwinge of the time, and will goe with the ſtreame though they drowne in the end. <hi>Ruffin</hi> vpon the Creede ſheweth no diſgrace can harme one for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, Chriſt for vs ſtooped to infirmities, and was borne of a Virgine, which humiliation was no ſtaine to his Diuinity, or blemiſh to his perſon, he prooueth it by a ſimilitude, <hi>Si quis vide at paruulum in profundo caeni necari, &amp;c.</hi> If a man of worth ſee a child ready to be choked in the mud, though he get ſome mire by pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3229:26"/>him out, can we account him deformed or pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: in like caſe let a man doe good, the aſperſions caſt vpon him can be no diſhonour. And how can he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the fauour of Chriſt, that playes the flincher, or if he belong to him not ſympathiſe in his diſgrace, Or to ſpeake of conuenient regards, how can he refuſe iuſtly to vndergoe a burden for Chriſt, that tooke ſo many loades of heauie cariage before for him. Infinite com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity might redound to his Kingdome by this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall fortitude, the ſtout reprehenſion of a ſinner might perhaps recall him at laſt, or make his proceedings more calme, and coole him where it could not ſaue him. The oppoſition of the wicked in a bad cauſe, or the helping of the weaker ſide in a good may meete with iarres, and rubs in the way, but the end which trieth all, ſhall crowne thoſe attempts with honour.</p>
            <p>But in ſtanding thus firmly with Chriſt, wiſdome and diſcretion muſt be guides, when there are apparent teſtimonies, no good can come, it is in vaine to ſtirre. One may better ſpare the labour, then put the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to a ſwearing man in a drunken fit, or counſaile a man bent to ſcorne and deriſion. Deuotion without circumſpection betrayes the truth, and counſell then looſeth the Maieſty with the ſucceſſe. <hi>To expect a fit time, to feare worſe inconueniences in them that are reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or to make them hate weake ones,</hi> non videtur cupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis occaſio, ſed conſilium Charitatis, <hi>ſuch forbearance is not an occaſion of caſe and luſt, but the counſaile of Charity</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſten. Solomons</hi> counſaile puts in this caution,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 1. <hi>de Ciu. Dei c.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Reproue not a ſcorner leaſt he hate thee, but rebuke a wiſe man and he will loue thee Pro.</hi> 9.8. Our Sauiour alſo did charge his Diſciples not to giue a holy thing to dogges, nor to caſt pearles before ſwine, One is ſet to barke againſt the truth, and the other to wallow in the mire of pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But when occaſion ſerueth, euery one is bound to ſtand with Chriſt, though it coſt him ſtrokes, better to indure them then the blowes of Gods indignation. A
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3229:27"/>white liuerd profeſſor is here diſclaimed: <hi>Hee that is not with me is againſt me.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>He that gathereth not with meſcattereth.</q>
            <p>The former point was directed againſt a ſinners negligence, this ouerturnes his confidence. The hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite hath a hope though it proue like a ſpiders web, he gathereth, but to ſmall purpoſe. If offenders had not in them this vaine humour, they would not heape ſo many ſinnes, nor treaſure vp ſo much wrath againſt the day of wrath. As the writers of morall Phyloſophie ſay all vertues doe meete in prudence, that knoweth how to carry things wiſely, ſo all vices ſeeme vnited in couetouſnes. For couetouſnes is called the roote of all euill, and too much gathering is the common diſeaſe of the times. View then all ſinnes comprehended in this, or this for all the reſt, their end is gathering, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can bring no happines. He that is gathering, is la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring and ſtill toiling. He is onely happy that leaues gathering, and maketh ſome vſe of his labours which is the true fruition of them. Some there are as men gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ouer to the captiuity of their baſe affections, which take no pleaſure but in raking together, nothing can be wrung away with cheerefulnes but comes like ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny drops of blood, whoſe mindes none if they were wiſe would haue for their wealth. For heaping vp wealth is like building, onely to delight in finiſhing the worke, and making good vſe of the poſſeſſion by imployment, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſt. 10. Ethic. 7.</note> Happines is in quiet, preſſe the word, we ſhall then find quiet, when we leaue gathering. From that ground the Phyloſopher could proue, felicity had no abſolute place in any worldly practiſe, for all things are paſſed ouer with care and trauell.
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.18.</note> The argument indeede is <hi>Solomons;</hi> when he conſidered the beſt gathering which he did wiſh for as the choifeſt; euen there, in much wiſdome he found griefe, and he that increaſeth knowledg, increaſeth, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, for care and trouble of the minde is not wanting
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3229:27"/>in thoſe labours; and in the next Chapter he comes to the ſweeteſt gathering, in compaſſing of pleaſures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a man muſt beſtow ſome trauell they at laſt doe tire and weary a man out: he proueth them vanitie and vexation of ſpirit. Nothing that ſauours of this life can be better, therefore no good gathering without Chriſt. But among all, the couetous toyling for eſtates, hath bundles to gather vp, fild with thornes and netles, abounding with difficulties and vexation: to remoue if it were poſſible a griping fiſt, hunting after commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity with too much eagernes. As if God would teach men by the rough and craggy paſſages, this was not his beſt way, and that he hath framed men according to his owne Image, &amp; giuen them a diuine ſoule for ſome other end then like a mole to dig in the earth, blinded with baſenes. Wherefore doe mens affections runne after <hi>Mammon</hi> in ſteed of God, or why doe they adore it in his roome? we call that euery ones God vpon which his deſires dote and runne, and ſo here, if wealth drowne all other cares, and poſſeſſe the minde as prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall. So bad is couetouſnes where it ſeemeth moſt harmeleſſe, what then where it worketh vpon aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage? and grateth vpon the neceſſities of others? In this age euery one ſtretcheth out all gaine to the vttermoſt, and the labours of the meaner ſort neuer leſſe regarded, one profeſſion ſtriueth to eate vp another. Yet haue we a general complaint of want, as if the curſe of ſcattering went along with this ſcraping. As faſt as the Tennant brings in, or the debter payes, pride and other moths, perhaps an vnthrifty ſonne, waſt and weare out all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Sometimes the labours of one in neede, when they as fertile fields ſhould returne to another, gaine with ſome aduantage: while too much vſe is made of them, ones eſtate and the others hope doe breake toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Suppoſe a miſerable gatherer may eſcape theſe miſeries, a ſcattering time will come at laſt, death will ſcatter the houſhold, and diuide the goods, it ſeuereth
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3229:28"/>the two neere friends ſoule and body, and for a time ſendeth them into remote and diſtant Countries. Then as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Iob 27.8.</note> 
               <hi>The hypocrite though hee gaineth where is his hope?</hi> Like the chaffe which the winde <hi>driueth</hi> from the face of the earth, or <hi>ſcattered</hi> as our Sauiour pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth here.</p>
            <p>If then we will gather and gaine too, we muſt ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Chriſt and we ſhall not ſcatter, Time imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his worſhip, though it be gone (as all time hath wings) ſtayeth in the booke of God, and bringeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Whatſoeuer labour in his ſeruice, or coſt is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed to maintaine and further it, is layd out ſafely. The choiſeſt graine lyeth longeſt in the earth, indures the ſtormes of Winter, but ſpringeth vp with a gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full crop: ſo the beſt workes haue their goodnes coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and longeſt tarry for recompence, but faithfull is he that promiſeth, an aſſured time ſhall bring them vp. <hi>Cast thy bread vpon the waters,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.1.</note> for after many daies thou ſhalt find it:</hi> To teach a worldly minde that ſeemeth to caſt all vpon waters, no benefite redounding backe (and therefore they caſt ſo little) that treaſure layd vp in heauen ſhall neuer be loſt. Let vs then gather time by taking opportunity to doe good. Let vs gather the word which Chriſt diſperſeth among vs as ſeede, or the ſoules Manna, which onely can feede it in the ſtaruing wilderneſſe of this life: Vſe it, or elſe it will putrifie as <hi>Manna</hi> did. From the iudgments and plagues of God, gather occaſions of admonition and repentance. And by this kind of gathering we ſhall get all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Open thy mouth wide and I ſhall fill it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 81.10</note> ſaith God to his people. His rewards are not like fruits of a cold bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolence, or a meane collection: but himſelfe, his Sonne, the firſt fruits of bleſſednes heere, and eternall glory hereafter in due time. In the naming whereof I may iuſtly make mine owne period, and yours. Inſtructions are gathered that we may diſperſe and publiſh them for others, to ſhew by precept and patterne, all gatherings
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3229:28"/>one day muſt haue a like concluſion. The end of Preaching is practiſe, and the end of practiſe is the end of all. Therefore let me winde vp theſe with our Sauiours counſell here, and S. <hi>Pauls</hi> in another place. So gather that you may not ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo runne that yee may obtaine.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
